The clouds adorning the setting sun whispered "It's gonna be your turn next" into my ear
But now that they've grown tired of just killing time I'm sure I'll just be their scapegoat
But I'm the king of my very own world
I can even run on top of water
I'm the egg who can put itself back together again after a fall
And can even go on to become an astronaut
I'm sure if I pick up all the beads that rained from the sky and gather them up
Then one day I'll finally be able to plant a flag which signifies my very own liberty
So I pull on my ripped jeans and fight back the tears the draft brings
I exhale a big gulp of air and then another 'cause I'm a boxer rising up again
You only get one chance to come back from the brink
So pound on that door you painted yourself
The colorful ink disperses into two paths
But you're the one who decides how your flower blooms
Midday Moon
What the hell is that?!
（林田(はやしだ)）なんじゃ そりゃ〜！
Grrr
Enough!
（林田）もういい！　俺が行く！
（零(れい)）アア…
I'm going!
So where is that junior high?!
（林田）どこ？　その中学
その担任の名前 なに？
What's the name of that homeroom teacher?!
I can understand why her older sister is worried!
確かに お姉さんの心配は分かる
From what I've heard,
that homeroom teacher is rotten to the core!
話聞いてるかぎり その担任…
明らかにマズイし！
Faculty Office
Mr. Hayashida! Calm down!
（零）
先生 暴れないで…　ウワッ！
Don't raise your voice to me.
（担任）
大きな声 出さないでちょうだい
I should really go!
（林田）
いっそ ホントに俺 行ったほうが…
Just let me go, Kiriyama!
（林田）つうか 行かせて 桐山(きりやま)！
（零）先生 落ち着いて！
Relax already!
As a fellow teacher, there's something I want to say to that homeroom teacher!
俺は 同じ教師として
その担任に言ってやりたいことが…
I know what you mean because I...
そんなこと言うなら
僕だって…
I want to go too!
僕だって行きたいですよ
（握りしめる音）
でも…
But...
知恵がない　役に立てない
I don't have the knowledge.
I can't be of any help.
In my own case, I'd pretend to be fine and just isolate myself.
（零）
自分のときだって 平気なフリして
ただ孤立だけして…
I didn't bother to struggle.
抵抗もしないで ただ我慢して
流されて 将棋に逃げて
Instead, I just endured it and went with the flow,
escaping into shogi.
So I don't have any useful wisdom in this situation!
だから こういうときに
役に立つ知恵も 何も持ってない
I thought if I could...
（零）お金だって…
せめて対局で勝って 稼いで…
at least make money by winning matches,
they could put it to good use somehow, so I tried my best.
何かに使ってもらえたらって
頑張ったけど…
（零）あの家の人たちは—
But they aren't the kind of people who would accept money from a total stranger like me.
赤の他人の僕に お金を
出させてくれる人たちじゃない
So please tell me, Mr. Hayashida!
だから 先生　教えてください
I'll treat you to oden or barbecue or whatever you want!
おでんでも焼き肉でも
何でも おごります！
Please lend me your wisdom!
知恵を貸してください！
（握りしめる音）
（林田）この…
You moron!
バカタレが！
Kiriyama!
桐山！
Heehee
"Please do me a favor. I'll buy you a drink later."
〝ちょっと頼まれてよ〞
〝あとで
１杯おごるからさ〞
Quit talking like you're my damn coworker!
…的なサラリーマン
みたいなこと—
Slap
言ってんじゃねえよ！
*Looks like he can't speak.
Certainly you've been working hard,
and maybe you make more money than me,
（林田）
お前は確かに 立派に働いてて
時には ムカつくことに—
which sometimes pisses me off,
俺より稼いだりも
すっかもしんないけど—
でも ここは学校で お前は
まだ たったの高校２年生で—
but this is a school,
and you're just a second-year high school student.
I'm a teacher!
俺は教師だ
Don't underestimate a teacher!
教師 ナメんなよ！
う〜ん…　まず ひなちゃんは—
First, I think Hina should change the person she's talking to.
話す相手を変えてみるのも
ありだと思う
Like the head teacher or the teacher of another subject...
学年主任とか 別の教科の先生とか
学校には 担任だけじゃない
Her homeroom teacher isn't the only option at school.
If that doesn't work,
it's okay for her to talk to another teacher.
話してダメだったら
ほかの先生に言ってみてもいいんだ
…で
その相手の親との話し合いだけど
And about speaking to the bully's parents...
Yeah, I don't think it'd go that far.
うん
多分 そこまではいかないと思う
Not in this case.
この状態だと
But if it does come to that,
it's true that her older sister alone would feel helpless.
（林田）でも
もし そんなことになったら—
確かに お姉さんだけじゃ
心細いのは 事実だ
お母さんは亡くなったんだよな？
Their mother passed away, right?
What about the father?
…で お父さんは？　何してるの？
What's he doing?
Well...
それは…
It's not a very pleasant story, so I'll just give you the basics.
（あかり）
あんまり愉快な話じゃないから
簡単に話すね
He told us he got a new girlfriend,
“新しい彼女ができたんだ”って
言ってね 出てっちゃったの
and then he just left us.
Now he's living in a new home and has another child.
今は 新しい家で
別の子のお父さんをやってるわ
Oh, that's right.
あっ そうだ
どら焼きあるの　食べる？
We have bean jam pancakes. Want some?
Sure.
はい
いただきます
Thank you.
（零）まるで—
It's as if...
she laid it out so it can mean nothing to her.
何でもないように話す姿に—
まだ 収めどころを
見つけられずにいる—
But I realized Akari's heart was floating around,
あかりさんの心が
ぽっかり浮かんでるのが分かった
unable to find a place to rest.
It wasn't that it was nothing to her.
何でもなくなったのではなく—
She still only talks about it as if it meant nothing to her.
何でもないようにしか
話せないのだ まだ
I see.
（林田）そっか…　う〜ん…
All the more reason that I have to go!
やっぱり
ますます俺が行くしかないな！
ええっ？　どこを
どう斜めに読んだら そうなるの？
How do you get that from this?
In fact, how would you even announce yourself when you arrive?
…ていうか
何て名乗って入り込む気ですか？
Rumble
As "Hina's friend's former homeroom teacher," of course!
“ひなさんの友人の
元担任ですが”に決まってるだろう
Rumble
That makes you complete strangers!
それを
“赤の他人”っていうんですよ！
Mr. Hayashida, you've already become a "demon teacher"!
もう既に先生が 自身が
モンスター教師になってますよ！
Grrr
If the bully will bring out her OPs,
もし相手が〝モンペ〞
出してくんなら…
*Short for "Overbearing Parents"
ニョキッ！
then we'll release the DT!
*Short for "Demon Teacher"
こっちは〝モン教〞
出すしかねえだろうが！
Am I wrong?! I'm not wrong, damn it!
違うか！
違わねえだろう こんちくしょう！
One would be as bad as the other...
もう既に
どっちも どっち…
*In terms of being a complete stranger!
Or are you even worse?
…ていうか
超えちゃってる
うわぁ！　助けて！
Help!
Oh yeah, also...
あっ！　あとな—
お金の件とかさ ホントに
自分で気づいてくれて良かったよ
About the money issue,
I'm glad you realized the futility yourself.
I'm relieved by that, sheesh.
ホッとしたよ もう…
When I thought about you going there with a bank statement and having a budget meeting for another family,
お前が
いきなり 通帳とか持って—
よそさまの家で
予算委員会とか開いてなくて
ヒヤヒヤしてたんだぜ
桐山がドン引かれちまうかもって
I was nervous.
I thought they might slam the door in your face.
Shake
Was planning
to do just that
Shake
On the way home, he bought me a steamed meat bun,
saying it was his "pride as a teacher."
（零）
帰り道 先生は—
“教師の意地だ”と言って
肉まんをおごってくれた
そして 僕は “ズレてる”とか
“頑固だ”とか—
And then he accused me of being "out of step" and "stubborn."
悪口ばかり言われた
Then he patted me on the back.
そして 背中をたたかれた
必要とされたい
だから 強くなりたい
"You want to be needed.
So you want to get better at shogi.
What's so wrong with that?"
“それの どこが不純なんだ”と
The calm mind
is the way
"Start by doing...
“お前は お前にできることを”…
Let's have a good match.
（棋士たち）よろしくお願いします
...what you're capable of, one thing at a time."
“まず
１コ１コやるしかないんだよ”と
"Take a deep breath,
“深く息をして—”
then put one foot in front of the other."
“１歩１歩 行くんだよ”と
負けました
I lost.
Thank you.
（２人）ありがとうございました
Hey, Kiriyama.
（横溝(よこみぞ)）おう 桐山
（零）あっ 横溝さん
Oh, Yokomizo.
Shogi Maestro Tournament
Morita Ichirou vs. Kiriyama Rei
Shogi Dragon Tournament
Kurasawa Keita vs. Mine Santa
Three white stars.
（横溝）
白星３つ　調子いいじゃないか
You're in fine form.
Thank you.
（零）ありがとうございます
（横溝）
新人戦決勝は 山崎順慶(やまざき じゅんけい)とだな
So your opponent in the Rookie Tournament finals is Yamazaki Junkei, huh?
頑張れよ 二海堂(にかいどう)の分まで
Good luck.
Do it for Nikaidou too.
I will.
はい
Rookie Tournament
Yamazaki
Kiriyama
Nikaidou
Hachiya
Kiriyama
Yamazaki
Nikaidou
Hachiya
Kiriyama
（二海堂）途中で負けんなよ！
Don't lose along the way!
俺とお前で
伝説を作るんだからな！
Because you and I are going to create a legend!
Idiot...
（零）バカ野郎…
After drilling that into my head, again and again...
あんなこと
さんざん言ってたくせに…
Nikaidou!
（零）二海堂…
So what's going on with Nikaidou?
（神宮寺(じんぐうじ)）
…で 二海堂は どうなんだ？
（零）あっ…
（神宮寺）大阪からは—
He can't return from Osaka for a while?
しばらく戻れんのか？
Yes.
（島田(しまだ)）はい
そのまま 大阪中央第一病院に
He's been admitted to Osaka First Central Hospital.
He'll be there a while for observation.
しばらく入院して
様子を見るそうです
Apparently it's difficult to move him closer.
移動は ちょっと難しいようで…
（零）島田さん
Shimada.
（島田）うん？
（零）それ…
What...
Kiriyama.
（島田）桐山…
...are you talking about?
どういうことですか？
Midday Moon
Adventurers
What are you talking about?
それ どういうことですか？
二海堂 入院って…
何かあったんですか？
Nikaidou's in the hospital?
Did something happen?
The expression on the adults' faces read "Oh, shoot,"
（零）“しまった”というような
大人２人の顔を見て—
so I figured it out right away.
すぐに分かった
I was the only one who didn't know.
知らなかったのは 僕だけなんだと
大したことないよ
It's nothing major.
あいつ
もともと体調悪かったのに—
He wasn't well to begin with,
so the strain of the Rookie Tournament semi-finals made his condition worse.
それが 新人戦の準決勝で
力んで悪化させたらしくて
（神宮寺）そうそう
さあ 島田　飲みに行くぞ
That's right.
Come on, Shimada. Let's get that drink.
待ってください！
Wait!
If this was his usual health downswing,
ただ体調崩しただけだったら—
that limousine with a bed or whatever could take him back here, right?
いつも
ベッド付きのリムジンでも—
何でも乗って
絶対 戻ってくるでしょう
He still has class-promotion matches!
順位戦だってあるのに…
But if he's in the hospital for a while...
でも しばらく入院って…
そんなに悪いんですか？
Is it that bad?
（島田）桐山
Kiriyama...
If you ask me and I can't answer, there must be a reason, right?
聞かれても 俺が答えないなら
何か理由があるからだよな？
You should understand that much.
そんくらい分かれ
The truth is I'd been faintly aware of it.
（零）
ホントは うすうす気づいてた
Hanaoka, who was always at his side,
いつも そばを離れない花岡(はなおか)さん
the beautifully decorated, faintly colored lunches,
美しく彩られた色の薄い弁当
all of the medications he always had in his bag...
いつも バッグの中に
見えていた たくさんの薬
The truth is I could never bring myself to ask about it.
ホントは ずっと聞けなかった
Ever since we were kids,
二海堂が 聞かれるのを
嫌がってたことぐらい—
I knew Nikaidou didn't like to be asked about it.
子供のころから分かってた
（零）そうですか…
Is that so?
In that case,
それなら…
ンンッ…　その理由ごと—
could I ask you what the reason itself is,
along with everything else?
全部 聞かせてもらうわけには
いきませんか？
（神宮寺）島田よ　俺 帰るわ
Shimada, I'm going home.
あと よろしくな
Take care of things.
桐山　メシでも食ってくか
Kiriyama.
Why don't we grab dinner?
After that, Shimada talked to me about Nikaidou.
（零）それから 島田さんは
二海堂のことを話してくれた
He talked about his "little brother" disciple.
弟弟子(おとうとでし)である男の子の話を
（島田）えっ？　また弟子を取る？
You're taking on another disciple?
Yeah.
（師匠）うむ…
You've always said that I would be your last disciple.
（島田）先生
弟子は もう私で最後だと—
ずっと
おっしゃってたじゃないですか
And you got sick last year, so why now?
去年 体も壊されたし
なんで また今…
Well, the thing is, I found an interesting child.
いやぁ だってさ 面白い子
見つけちゃったんだものさ
To become a shogi professional,
you first have to join the association.
（島田）将棋のプロになるには
まず 奨励会に入らねばならない
And to do that, you have to be under someone's wing.
そして それには必ず
誰かの弟子にならないといけない
Tiny
And so, a fourth grader came over.
そうして やって来たのが
小学４年生の坊だった
Shine
Nice to meet you!
（二海堂）
はじめまして　二海堂晴信(はるのぶ)です！
I'm Nikaidou Harunobu!
うん…
これが島田六段　お前の兄ちゃんだ
This is Shimada, 6-dan.
He's your big brother.
You two get along, got it?
（師匠）仲良くな
（島田）丸っこいな
He's so round.
Huh? Where have I...
あれ？　この子 どこかで…
その子には 見覚えがあった
I remembered him from somewhere.
I'd seen him when I was a guest lecturer at a children's tournament.
子供大会のゲストで
講師をやったときに見かけた子だ
What's with the round kid?
（来場者Ａ）
何だ？　あの真ん丸い子
じいやに弁当 持たせて…
He's making an old man carry his lunch.
I heard he pulled up in a fancy car.
（来場者Ｂ）
下に すごい車で乗りつけたって
What a stuck-up.
（来場者Ａ）感じ悪っ！
This is probably a rich kid's pastime.
（来場者Ｂ）どうせ金持ちの道楽だ
すぐにいなくなるさ
He won't be around for long.
（花岡）
さあ　よ〜く かんで　30回ですぞ
Now chew well. Thirty times each bite.
Okay.
A special lunch, huh?
特製弁当か
ハァ…　金持ちのボンボンが
Spoiled rich kid.
Why go to all the trouble of joining this world?
なんで わざわざ こんな世界に？
漫画でも ゲームでも
いくらでも買ってもらえるだろうに
I'm sure his parents would buy him
whatever manga or video games he wanted.
少年時代 貧乏で苦しんだ俺は
たちまち 彼をやっかんだ
I was envious of him, since I lived in poverty when I was a kid.
Well, I'm sure he won't stick with it.
まあ どうせ続かないだろう
Video games and computers are more fun.
ゲームとかパソコンのほうが
楽しいもんな
Children's
Shogi
Tournament
Thank you for your patience.
（司会）お待たせしました
それでは決勝戦を行います
It's now time for the finals.
（司会）東京都杉並(すぎなみ)区 桐山零君！
From Suginami Ward, Tokyo, Kiriyama Rei!
（島田）ふ〜ん…
So the spoiled rich kid lost in the semi-finals.
さっきのボンボン
準決で負けたのか
ふ〜ん…　意外に頑張ったな
He did better than I expected.
I was shocked when I saw the match records.
（島田）棋譜を見て 驚いた
Wh-What is this?
（島田）な… 何だ？　これ
お互い 居玉の超力戦…
All-out war, with both of them having sitting kings?
And 185 moves...
しかも 185手…
ホントに小学生の将棋か？
Is this really elementary school shogi?
Is he okay?
（係員）
大丈夫ですか？　今 救急車を
I'll call an ambulance.
大丈夫です
救急車は必要ありません
He'll be fine.
There's no need for an ambulance.
The car is waiting downstairs.
車は下に待たせてありますゆえ
From the old man's calm demeanor,
（島田）
その老人の落ち着いた対応に—
I caught a glimpse of the boy's long fight against illness.
少年の長い闘病生活が
かいま見えた
Shogi is honest.
将棋っていうのは正直だ
勉強した分しか うまくならない
The only way to get good at it is by studying.
そう　ここにあるものは—
That's right.
What I had in my hand were the match records of
someone who threw a happy childhood to the winds.
楽しい子供時代なんて
平気で かなぐり捨てた—
ひとりの人間の棋譜だった
No, that's not right.
いや 違う　彼は—
He never even had the kind of childhood that could be flung away.
投げ捨てられるほどの
子供時代なんて—
はなから持ってはいなかったのだ
う… うわ…　でっけえ
It's huge.
There is No Correct
Answer in Shogi
Sh-Shimada, 6-dan!
し… 島田六段！
That's okay.
ああ いいんだよ
横になってくれ…
Lie down.
I've come in our mentor's place for today.
今日は 師匠の代わりに来たんだよ
（二海堂）ンッ…
（島田）師匠 神経痛で—
He's got nerve pain right now, so he can't move.
今 動けなくってな
Excited to see an actual professional shogi player
Here. These are from him.
（島田）はい　これ 師匠から
“古いけど いいのか”って…
He said they're old, but I hope that's okay.
うわぁ！　挿絵入りの初版だ！
Treasure Island
Twenty Thousand Leagues Under the Sea
They're illustrated first editions!
When I asked him if he wanted to play...
（島田）
“一局 指すか”と言ったら…
Really?!
いいんですか？
（島田）青黒い顔に 赤みが差した
...some color came to his pasty face.
And so I would play him from time to time.
こうして
俺は 彼と時々 指すようになった
He would always give it everything he had,
彼は いつでも全力で…
and beating him always required much effort.
負かすのに いつも骨が折れた
But one day, I hurt him.
だが ある日 彼を傷つけてしまった
His health had taken a turn for the worse,
体調をひどく悪化させ
連敗を続けていた彼を—
and he'd been on a losing streak,
so the idea was to encourage him.
勇気づけたくて
やってしまったことだった
Please don't hold back like that!
（二海堂）
そういう手加減はしないでください
坊…
Kiddo.
If I'm treated as a weakling even when I play shogi,
将棋でまで
弱い人間扱いされたら—
where am I supposed to live?!
もう僕は
どこで生きていったら
いいんですか？
His disease is incurable,
so it would be with him for the rest of his life.
（島田）
彼の病は 難病とされるもので—
一生 つきあっていかねば
ならないものだった
Kiddo, I'm sorry.
（島田）坊…　すまなかった
I promise to never do it again.
もう二度と こんなことしないから
He had strict dietary restrictions.
（島田）厳しい食事制限
His days went by enduring, holding his breath, and hoping his condition wouldn't deteriorate.
悪化させぬように ひたすら耐えて
息を殺すように過ごす日々
He could hardly do anything.
ケンカもスポーツも—
Fighting, sports, and playing with
friends were all out of the question.
友達と遊ぶことすら
ほとんど全て かなわなかった
The only place where he could run about as a hero
彼が唯一 ヒーローとなって
暴れ回ることができるのは—
were on the 81 squares of this board.
この たった81マスの
盤上のみなのだ
（島田）
桐山　これが今日の準決勝の棋譜だ
Kiriyama.
These are the match records of today's semi-finals.
Big Brother, please don't tell Kiriyama about my disease.
（二海堂）兄者…　病気のことは
桐山には言わないでください
A rival is essential to getting better at shogi.
強くなるには ライバルが必須です
He doesn't realize it himself, but he's a kind person.
あいつは
自分じゃ気づいてないけど—
優しい人間です
And he's unstable.
そして 不安定だ
If he knew about this, he'd lose his touch.
知ったら きっと手が鈍ります
Then I wouldn't be able...
そしたら 僕は もう…
to get any better.
これ以上 強くなれない
The match record was two pages long.
（零）棋譜は２枚あった
持ち時間をフルに使った最初の一局
In the first match, he used all the time available.
He was in the inferior position, but he stuck it out,
（零）
劣勢だった将棋を粘りに粘って
優勢に転じた その直後—
and right as he turned it around,
his opponent had a fourfold repetition.
相手による千日手
その果ての指し直し
Near the end of the ensuing rematch,
そこからの１分将棋による
魂を絞り出すような138手
after 138 moves that wrung out his soul,
with only one minute allowed per move...
Kiriyama.
桐山
お前は それでも 二海堂に—
Can you still be merciless to Nikaidou?
こんな むごいことを
してやれるか？
I'm going to the finals.
行ってきます 決勝戦
All right.
The Rookie Tournament finals were held a week later at the Kansai Shogi Hall.
（零）新人戦決勝戦は
１週間後 関西将棋会館にて
あっ ヤバイ　降ってきた
Crap. It's really coming down.
Well, we're near the train station.
いっか　駅まで近いし
Make a run for it?
（島田）走るか
（零）はい
Okay.
（零）
細い銀の糸みたいな雨の中—
As we were running in rain that looked like thin, silver threads,
走りながら 僕は
二海堂の棋譜を思い出していた
I thought back on Nikaidou's match record.
迷い ためらい ひるみながらも…
Though he was hesitant and faltered and flinched,
he had faith in himself,
それでも 自分の今までを信じて…
so he aimed for the promised land
憧れの地 目指して…
and raced ahead like a fireball.
火の玉みたいに突き進む
Those two pages...
まるで 一編の…
read like an adventure novel.
冒険小説のようだった
Adventurers
I wonder why I'm smiling
The night wears on as I trace it with a finger
In the oversized nooks of this world
My heart continues to melt away
Like the petals of a flower repelling the rain yet refusing to wither
All the things important to me have spilled out
Before I knew it I was all alone and I'd walked a great distance
I'd forgotten what my own voice really sounded like
And it was the strangest feeling
After dawn broke on that long night
I remembered as if it were all a dream
I gave myself up to that nostalgic eternity
And it seems like I can go on walking again
Next Episode Preview
Episode 31
Nikaidou kept playing
until he collapsed.
（零）倒れるまで
指し続けた二海堂
And the girl in front of me...
そして
目の前の彼女も…
I have a feeling that I need to go.
（ひなた）行かなきゃ
ダメな気がする
I swear I'll win before I come home.
（零）僕は絶対に
勝って帰ってくるから
Thank you, Kiriyama.
（ひなた）
ありがとう 桐山君
Huh?
（零）
あれ？　ここ どこだ？
Where am I?
Illustration: Ueda Hajime
Kiriyama, next time let's have
dinner together with Kiddo.
（島田）桐山
次は 坊も一緒に
メシに行こうな